Guide to the Nina Berberova Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nina Berberova collection
1900-2001
1968-1993
GEN MSS 573
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.27
(18 boxes)
The Nina Berberova Collection contains correspondence, writings, printed material, photographs, audiovisual recordings and electronic files by and relating to Nina Berberova, especially the latter decades of her life. The material was collected and donated by Murl Barker and John Malmstad.
Other storage formats: electronic files.
Berberova, N. (Nina), 1901-1993
Berberova, N. (Nina.) ( Bii︠a︡nkurskie prazdniki i drugie rasskazy)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Malmstad, 2004 and Murl Barker, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 18: Restricted fragile material. Reference copies are available for electronic documents. Consult Access Services for further information. For other materials, reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 19 (audio cassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Nina Berberova Papers, GEN MSS 182
Existence and Location of Copies
Audiocassettes have been reformatted as digital files.
Nina Nikolaevna Berberova (1901-1993)
Nina Nikolaevna Berberova was born on August 8, 1901 (July 26, 1901, old style) in St. Petersburg, Russia. Her autobiography, Kursiv moi (first published in English as The Italics are Mine ), details her life as an emigre and writer up to approximately 1957.
After living in Paris for twenty five years, Berberova emigrated to the United States in 1950. She began her academic career in 1958 at Yale University. She continued to write while she was teaching, publishing several povesti, critical articles and some poetry. She left Yale in 1963 for Princeton University, where she taught until her retirement in 1971. For Berberova "retirement" meant visiting as a lecturer at Cornell, Columbia, Bryn Mawr and the University of Pennsylvania, teaching during the summer in the Russian School at Middlebury College, and writing. During these years she was awarded honorary degrees from Glasboro State College (1980), Middlebury College (1983), and Yale University (1992).
In 1991 Berberova moved from Princeton, New Jersey to Philadelphia. She lived there until she died September 27, 1993 from complications from a fall.
Readers may consult Nina Berberova Papers, GEN MSS 182 for further description of Nina Berberova's life and work.
Scope and Contents
The Nina Berberova Collection contains correspondence, writings, printed material, photographs, audiovisual recordings and electronic files by and relating to Nina Berberova. The material was collected and donated by Murl Barker and John Malmstad and mostly relates to the later decades of Berberova's life.
Series I was collected and donated by Berberova's former student Murl Barker, whom she met in the early 1960s at Yale University. They continued a close friendship until Berberova's death in 1993. Barker's collection includes correspondence, writings, printed material, photographs, audiovisual recordings and electronic files documenting Berberova's career, especially after her emigration to the United States in 1950.
Series II, donated by John Malmstad, consists chiefly of letters from Berberova to Malmstad.
Many of the relationships, writings and events documented in this collection are also documented in the Nina Berberova Papers, GEN MSS 182. Barker's letters to Berberova are in her papers, while Berberova's letters to Barker are in this collection. Berberova's papers contain material related to many of her publications; additional typescripts and holograph notes are in this collection. This collection contains two holograph journals and one photocopy of a journal that are not in Berberova's papers.
Arrangement
The Nina Berberova Collection is organized into two series: Murl Barker Collection of Nina Berberova and John Malmstad Collection of Nina Berberova.
Authors, Russian -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, Russian -- 20th Century; Russia -- Emigration and immigration; Russian literature -- 20th Century; Audiocassettes; Photographs; Videotapes; Barker, Murl; Berberova, N. (Nina), 1901-1993; Malmstad, John E., 1941-
- Murl Barker Collection of Nina Berberova, 1927-2001; Series I; 5.05; (14 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into five subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Personal Papers and Effects, Photographs and Artwork and Audiovisual Material.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains papers collected by Berberova's student Murl Barker. These include correspondence, typescripts and drafts of Berberova's writings and Barker's writings on Berberova, photographic snapshots and portraits and audiovisual recordings of Berberova's interviews and readings.
  - Correspondence
    Correspondence is organized under two headings. Berberova's correspondence is filed first. Barker's correspondence related to Berberova follows.
    Most of the correspondence in this subseries consists of letters from Berberova to Murl Barker. The letters are largely personal, documenting Berberova's travels, relationships, navigation through American life and the growth of her literary recognition. Later letters address legal and administrative topics regarding Berberova's estate and papers.
    - Berberova, Nina
      - Barker, Jackie, outgoing, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Barker, Murl, outgoing, 1962-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2-16)
      - Barker, Murl, outgoing, 1986-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-20)
      - Barker, Murl, outgoing, typed copies, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
      - Ingram Merrill Foundation, incoming and outgoing, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Katanian, Vasilii and Inna, incoming, 1993 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 24)
        Sent via Vitalii Vul'f; accompanied by a copy of a 1973 letter from Berberova to Lili IUr'evna [Brik]
      - Knizhnaia Palata [publisher], outgoing, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Lopez, Leonard, incoming, 1993 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Miller, Ron, outgoing, 1963-1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Barker, Murl
      - Correspondence related to Nina Berberova, 1993-2001 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Writings
    Writings are organized under six headings: Books, Stories, Poetry, Plays, Subject Files and Murl Barker Writings on Berberova. Under each heading, works are arranged alphabetically. Two groups of documents labeled "Unpublished by Nyssen" and "Stories discarded" are filed at the end of Stories.
    The writings in this series are mostly drafts and copies of Berberova's stories that reflect the editorial process of producing collected volumes. Several folders contain the stories published in Biiankurskie Prazdniki. Some early stories from Russian emigre newspaper publications in Paris are labeled "discarded." Berberova very lightly corrected or annotated some of these. In addition to stories, writings by Berberova include one play, one folder of poems in English, the introduction to a 1997 edition of her biography of Chaikovskii and two subject files.
    The subseries also contains collected writings by Murl Barker about Berberova, including several short papers and biographical entries. These papers include one computer disk.
    - Books
      - Chaikovskii, Introduction, typescript, copy, circa 1997 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Stories
      All are copies of printed versions unless otherwise noted
      - "Aktery", undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Biiankurskie Prazkniki i Drugie Rasskazy, copy of typescript and manuscript draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 31-33)
      - "Chernaia Bolezn'", undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - "Ego supruga", undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - "Mysliashchii trostnik", undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Oblegchenie uchasti, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - "Pamiati Shlimana", undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - "Rasskazy 1931-1940 g.g.," typescript, copy, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
        Accompanied by a note by Murl Barker
      - "Soobshchniki", undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - "Strashnyi sud", undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - "Unpublished by Nyssen", undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
        Accompanied by notes by Murl Barker
      - "Stories discarded" (short stories)
        This group of stories is arranged in the order in which it was received.
        Unless otherwise noted, the short stories filed together under the label of "Stories discarded" are printed versions (some accompanied by photocopies). Although no positive identification is evident, the printed versions dating from the 1930s are likely clippings from Poslednie Novosti [ The Latest News ], a Russian emigre journal published in Paris. Some copies were made from the B.I. Nicolaevsky Collection at the Hoover Institution, Stanford University.
        - "Baryni," printed version from Russkaia Mysl' and copy, circa 1980s, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
        - "Zoia Andreevna", 1927, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
        - "Kogda my, mertvye, ne probuzhdaemsia", [1933], undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
        - "Miesta rodnyia", [1933], undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
        - "V chistilishchie," copies, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
        - "Istoricheskii razskaz", [1933] (Box 4, Folder 48)
        - "Pervyi angazhement", [1933] (Box 4, Folder 49)
        - "Starshii Brat," typescript and copy, [1934], undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
        - "Probavshiia Deti," copy, undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
        - "Kometa," typescript and copy, [1939], undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
        - "Paskhal'nyi sjurpriz", [1932] (Box 4, Folder 53)
        - "Ona byla", [1930s], undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
        - "Pieshkom v Siian'", [1930s], undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
        - "Mechta o ravnoviesii," copies, undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
        - "Voobrazhaemyia prikliucheniia," copies, undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
        - Untitled story, copies, [1932] (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Poetry
      - "My English Poems," holograph and typescript, 1974-1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - "Poems after 1985," holograph and typescript, 1982, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - "Poems recorded by Nina Berberova," typescript, copy, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Plays
      - Malen'kaia Devochka typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 62-64)
      - Little Girl, English translation of Malen'kaia Devochka, typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Subject files
      - "IA sama o sebe," holograph and typescript notes, 1932, 1970s, undated (Box 5, Folder 66-67)
        Includes: portions of a journal from 1932, holograph; accompanied by letter from Nelja
      - Solzhenitsyn notes and writings, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 68)
        Includes clippings, notes and copies of the typescript for Berberova's "Notes on Solzhenitsyn's novel 'August 1914'"
    - Murl Barker writings on Berberova
      - Notes and drafts, 1990s (Box 5, Folder 69-74)
        Includes notes and drafts related to Barker's speeches, articles and reviews about Berberova and preface to Biiankurskie Prazdniki
      - Notes and drafts of writings and transcripts of letters, 1990s (Box 5, Folder EF)
        Conditions Governing Access
        [Access available through Public Services, Disk#1]
  - Personal Papers and Effects
    Personal papers are arranged roughly chronologically.
    The subseries contains journals, personal papers, ephemera and personal effects. The personal papers include legal, financial and medical papers.
    Many of Berberova's journals are located in the Nina Berberova Papers (GEN MSS 182), a separately cataloged collection. The additional journals and diaries in this series complement that collection.
    - Address book, circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - "Parizhskii dnevnik," journal, holograph and copy, 1986 February-March (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - "Evropa," journal, holograph and copy, 1986 June-July (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Journal, photocopy, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Legal, financial and medical papers, 1990s (Box 6, Folder 79-80)
    - Ephemera and correspondence related to honorary degree from Yale, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Marriage certificate of George Kochevitskii and Nina Berberova, 1954 September 15 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - "Zapiski iz publiki" [Notes from the public], manuscript, [1989 September] (Box 6, Folder 83-85)
      These slips of paper contain questions posed by members of the audience during Berberova's public appearance(s) in Moscow in 1989
    - Printed material about Nina Berberova, 1990s (Box 7, Folder 86-89)
    - Obituaries, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Death notices, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Printed material and ephemera from the Colloque international Nina Berberova, Arles, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Box of personal effects, undated (Box 8)
      This box of personal effects contains a medal from Berberova's designation as Chevalier of the Order of Arts and Letters (France, 1989), three watches, one ring, one chain and a small purse
  - Photographs and Artwork
    Dated photographs are arranged chronologically followed by one folder of undated photographs. One oil painting is filed at the end of the subseries.
    Almost all photographs are of Berberova and most are snapshots, although a few are professional portraits. Most of the photographs have been identified by Murl Barker and the folder descriptions reflect his notes. Besides Berberova, identified subjects include Murl and Jackie Barker, George Kochevitskii, Marcello Mastroianni and Hubert and Christine Nyssen.
    - In New York with George Kochevitskii, 1954-1955 (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Various locations, snapshots and one portrait, includes negatives, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 94)
    - In Seattle, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - In Washington State with Murl and Jackie Barker, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - Thanksgiving in Philadelphia, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Snapshots and copy of photograph from early twentieth century, 1970s (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - In Glassboro (honorary degree), 1980 (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - In Middlebury (honorary degree), 1983 (Box 9, Folder 100)
    - In Princeton, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - In Philadelphia, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - Portraits by J.L. Aucagos, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - In Princeton and Paradou with Hubert and Christine Nyssen, 1987-1989 (Box 9, Folder 104)
    - In Arles, includes negatives, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 105-107)
    - In Strassbourg, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 108)
    - Portraits by Kathleen Blumenfeld, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 109)
    - In Princeton with Hubert and Christine Nyssen, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 110)
    - In Philadelphia, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 111)
    - In New Haven, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 112)
    - In Philadelphia, includes negatives, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 113)
      Some with Marcello Mastroianni
    - In Philadelphia, includes negatives, 1991-1992 (Box 9, Folder 114-115)
    - In New Haven (Yale honorary degree), includes negatives, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 116-117)
    - Portrait by Arturo Patton, 1992
    - In Philadelphia, 1992-93 (Box 10, Folder 118)
    - Murl Barker and Hubert Nyssen disposing of Berberova's ashes, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 119)
    - Album of photographs and copies from early 1900s to 1992, circa 1993 (Box 10, Folder 120)
      Accompanied by a list of identifications in French
    - Snapshots and portraits, undated (Box 10, Folder 121)
    - Untitled oil painting by Nikolai Makeev, undated
  - Audiovisual Material
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Audiocassettes have been reformatted as digital files. The original cassettes are filed in Restricted Fragile and may be accessed only with the permission of the curator.
    Audiovisual Material is organized under two headings: Audiocassettes and Videocassettes. Under each heading material is arranged roughly chronologically. Undated material is filed at the end of each heading.
    Audiovisual material contains recordings of Berberova reading poetry, interviews with Berberova and unidentified material. Folder titles are based on notes and labels accompanying the cassettes.
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Audiocassettes
      - Moscow, 1976; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002099365927)
        "Lily Brik to NB via Murl Barker"
      - Berberova lectures on Russian poetry (in Russian) (1 of 2 audiocassettes), 1977 March 22; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002099365935)
      - Berberova lectures on Russian poetry (in Russian) (2 of 2 audiocassettes), 1977 March 22; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002099365943)
      - Berberova in France (French interviews), 1986 Spring; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002099365950)
      - Berberova reading poetry, from Nadine Kreks (bad fidelity), undated; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002099365968)
      - Lecture de Poèmes par N. Berberova, undated; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002099365976)
      - Berberova reading poetry, undated; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002099365984)
      - Berberova lectures on Russian poetry (in Russian), 1977 March 22; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002099366008)
        There is a copy of this audiocassette.
      - Berberova lectures on Russian poetry (in Russian), 1977 March 22; 1 (Box 11, Item barcode 39002099365992)
    - Videocassettes
      - "Nina, Apostrophe", 1989 April; 1 (Box 12, Item barcode 39002099366016)
        This appears to be a duplicate.
      - "Nina, Apostrophe", 1989 April; 1 (Box 12, Item barcode 39002099366024)
      - "Nina Berberova, Apostrophes LP", 1989 April; 1 (Box 12, Item barcode 39002099366032)
      - "Voices of Leningrad, excerpts of interview", [1990]; 1 (Box 12, Item barcode 39002099366040)
        Accompanied by a manuscript note listing the names of Russian literary figures
      - Sodaperaga [production company]. "Nina Berberova, 1ère partie", undated; 1; Running time: 53 minutes, 33 seconds; Videocassette not digitized. Unsupported format. (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099366057)
        Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
        SECAM format
      - Sodaperaga [production company]. "Nina Berberova, 2ème partie, L'Allegement du Destin", undated; 1; Running time: 51 minutes, 35 seconds; Videocassette not digitized. Unsupported format. (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099366065)
      - Sodaperaga [production company]. "Un siècle d'écrivains, Nina Berberova", undated; 1; Running time: 46 minutes (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099366073)
        PAL format
      - "NB, Guy's", undated; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099366081)
      - "Not for USA", undated; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099366099)
- John Malmstad Collection of Nina Berberova, 1969-1988, undated; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  The papers donated by John Malmstad chiefly consist of letters written to him by Berberova. The letters are largely personal but they also document Berberova's progress in publishing her work and her interest in the literary legacy of Vladislav Khodasevich. In addition to correspondence, the series contains one folder of other papers and one photograph portrait.
  - Correspondence, Nina Berberova to John Malmstad, 1969-1988, undated (Box 15, Folder 139-140)
  - Other papers from John Malmstad, 1968-1973 (Box 15, Folder 141)
    Includes: course syllabus, lecture notes, copy of newspaper clipping
  - Turner, Orren Jack, photographic portrait of Nina Berberova, undated (Box 15, Folder 142)
- Oversize, 2.59; (2 boxes)
  - Printed material about Berberova (Series I), 1990s (Box 16, Folder 143-144)
  - Portrait by Arturo Patton (Series I), 1992 (Box 17, Folder 145)
  - Untitled oil painting by Nikolai Makeev (Series I), undated (Box 17, Folder 146)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.63; (1 box)
  Boxes 18-19 contain fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order and may be accessed only with the permission of the appropriate curator. Access to electronic files is available through public services. Reference copies of audio recordings have been substituted in the main files for reference use.
  - Box 4, folder 45 (Box 18, Folder 147)
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies are available for electronic documents. Consult Access Services for further information. For other materials, reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 4, folder 48 (Box 18, Folder 148)
  - Box 4, folder 49 (Box 18, Folder 149)
  - Box 4, folder 53 (Box 18, Folder 150)
  - Box 4, folder 54 (Box 18, Folder 151)
  - Box 5, Disk #1 (Box 18, Folder 152)